(Overwatch theme music)
- [Hammeh] And welcome.
I'm Hammeh, and in this series,
we're discovering the lore, backstory,
and characters of Overwatch's
heroes, including more detail
through their in-game voice
lines and interactions.
Before any map starts
and during the game on various triggers,
Overwatch heroes chatter
with and react to each other
in some funny ingame ways.
These give us some great extra insights
into hero character,
interests, and backstories too.
In this video, we're
looking at Roadhog's story
through his interactions with other heroes
and the world around him.
Currently an internationally
wanted criminal,
the life of Mako Rutledge
wasn't always this way.
Once a rebel with a cause,
following the theft and
then destruction of his home
and the lands around
it, he's now only known
as the ruthless wanted killer
and internationally
wanted criminal Roadhog.
Firstly, we'll discover
Roadhog's background
and origin story.
In an Overwatch future,
Omnica Corporations Omnium's
promised to revolutionise
robotic manufacturing.
The automated construction machinery,
backed by self improving
software algorithms,
were set to usher in a new economic age
on par with the industrial revolution
or the invention of the production line
in the history books.
Installed on every continent
and powered by fusion cores,
Australia's omnium was
located in the outback,
which was only populated with
a scattering of solar farmers,
survivalists, and those
seeking solitude at the time.
When the First Omnic Crisis struck
and waves of omnics emerged from omniums
that were thought to be defunct,
the residence of the Australian outback
would've been first in the line of fire.
Australia as a country
was hit particularly hard,
almost being destroyed as
a result in the conflict.
After the crisis was brought to an end
by the actions of Overwatch,
it appears that unlike the
uncommunicative omnic forces
that had started the
war, by its conclusion,
there were independent, self aware omnics,
even with omnic central
command protocols destroyed
and with the God AIs that
played some part in the crisis
put into containment.
The Australian government,
rebuilding like so many other countries,
must have had a large enough
amount of these omnics
remaining in Australia to
consider drastic action
and to be forced to negotiate.
In an attempt to
establish a longterm peace
with these remaining
omnics, government officials
gifted them the Australian
omnium and the surrounding area
in a reservation style agreement.
And in this attempted peace deal,
nearby residents ended up
losing their homes as a result,
including a young Mako Rutledge,
possibly in his early
twenties at the time.
We know nothing of Mako's early years,
but perhaps there's
some clues in his skins,
with the toa, tribal looking skin.
Toa are small artefacts made by members
of one south Australian aboriginal tribe,
so perhaps that's a hint
as to some of Mako's
ancestry in some form.
Whatever his past, young
Rutledge was furious
at the sacrifice of his home,
and joined other similar minded people
and forming the Australian
Liberation Front,
an organisation dedicated
to taking back the land
that their government
had given to the omnics.
Fighting escalated until
the rebels sabotaged
the omnium's fusion core,
resulting in a fusion explosion
that destroyed the facility,
irradiated the surrounding
region with fallout,
and littering the outback
with debris and metal
for kilometres around, forever altering
the landscape of the area.
Amidst this wreckage,
there were some survivors.
Some people banded together
and called themselves the junkers,
scavenging the husk of the omnium,
recovering metal,
components, and other salvage
and formed a lawless, cutthroat
society in its shadow.
The main settlement in the
area became known as Junkertown
and this would be a key location
in not only the stories
of not only Roadhog,
but also Junkrat.
Mako watched as his home
became an apocalyptic wasteland
and he changed forever,
in attempting to adapt
to this new, broken world
he once called home.
Becoming a junker
enforcer, he donned a mask,
took to the highways of the outback
in the area surrounding the omnium,
and little by little,
the person that he was
became a thing of the past.
The last vestiges of Mako's
personality faded away
and Roadhog was born.
Known as a ruthless killer
with a well earned reputation
for cruelty and destruction,
Roadhog's currently
working as a bodyguard,
keeping Junkrat safe in
exchange for a 50/50 share
of whatever valuable secret he discovered
in the husk of the Australian omnium.
Whether they're escaping
the gangs and bounty hunters
after Junkrat or just
expanding their horizons,
the pair have now left the outback
and are currently embarked on
an international crime spree.
We've seen them in the UK in King's Row,
stealing the crown jewels,
robbing the vault in
Dorado, Mexico for gold,
and even breaking into
ice cream trucks in Paris
and taking arcade toys in
what may be Hanamura, Japan.
We also know that Roadhog
as been through Sydney
before travelling worldwide,
as detailed in their comic, Going Legit,
when what they thought
was a legitimate job
turned out to be a setup
for an insurance scam.
The pair got an explosive
and murderous revenge
with the presumed death of
the CEO or senior member
of a company called Hyde Global.
The motto of apparently no job
too big, no score too small,
and gracing crimestopper
programmes the world over,
will a similarly reluctant
Mako get his share
of Junkrat's treasure?
Is the criminal life all there is now
for the displaced Junker,
as he's almost entering his fifties?
There's one thing we
can definitely count on:
as long as he's teamed up with
the anarchaic Jamison Fawkes,
trouble is never going to be far away
for the hog of our hearts.
Whatever kind of person he was
before the Ausralian omnium's destruction,
Roadhog's certainly a
man of violent actions
and few words now.
In fact, a lot of his words
are to do with violence.
- [Roadhog] Welcome to the apocalypse.
Violence is usually the answer.
I'm a one man apocalypse.
Go on, ask me what the other one says.
It says left.
- [Hammeh] However, humour wise,
Roadhog does see the
funny side of some things,
even if it's mostly violence related.
He's clearly a fan of pigs
from his various stickers,
ornaments on his bike, and other things
and there's quite a few
references to those too.
- [Roadhog] Here, little piggy.
Say bacon one more time.
Oops. (chuckling)
Want some candy?
- [Hammeh] As well as the most threatening
Halloween statement I've probably heard.
And when Roadhog kills enemy Reaper,
he'll occasionally throw
out a little sarcastic,
in my head anyway, compliment
- [Roadhog] Nice mask.
- [Hammeh] From one
mask wearer to another.
- [Roadhog] No pain, no gain.
- [Hammeh] In terms of that
last line, I doubt he's talking
in the fitness motivational sense there.
Someone else's pain will probably result
in some gain for Roadhog and Junkrat.
Although he's known as
a criminal killer now,
Roadhog does have a philosophical side
that comes out from time to time.
Here's some examples of his musings.
- [Roadhog] Everyone has a plan,
till they get punched in the mouth.
Life is pain, so is death. (chuckling)
Only thing you can count
on in this broken world.
We're all animals.
What's mine, is mine.
- [Hammeh] And it does feel
like occasional flashes
of a person beyond the violent killer
that Roadhog is known as now.
He occasionally expresses
very out of character
or opposite sentiments to his desires
for violence and destruction.
- [Roadhog] Pretty.
Thanks for noticing me.
Aw, that's no fun.
I need my space.
- [Hammeh] In some of
the clips, we see Roadhog
is stealing things like ice cream
or robbing an ice cream truck,
taking away handfuls
of toys from an arcade.
He does have this
mildly, how can I put it,
childish flash of innocence, maybe,
a more sombre, not Sombra, personality.
Indeed, thanks for noticing me,
that line is also a line that Eeyore says
in the Winnie the Pooh children's books,
if you're familiar with those.
Eeyore is a bit of a gloomy donkey,
bit of a pessimist,
and kind of just wants
to be included and liked.
That does feel similar
to some of the vibes
that I think Roadhog gives on occasion.
What do you reckon?
Okay, time for the reference game.
There's not a huge amount
with our Hog friend,
but I'll leave a gap as always
so you can have a guess at this one.
- [Roadhog] So much
trauma going on in L-B-C,
it's kind of hard being Road H-O-single-G.
- [Hammeh] That's from the
famous Snoop Dogg track,
Gin and Juice of course.
Can't believe that's 20+ years old now.
LBC, Long Beach City, California,
hip hop home of Warren G amongst others.
I'll leave it to folks
more educated than I am
in hip hop history to
take over from there.
But Roadhog, clearly a fan.
That one's not actually
in the game anymore,
I don't think, so maybe it was left out
for copyright reasons.
Reference wise, of course,
Roadhog is a whole bunch of references
in terms of Junkenstein's Revenge.
The presence of Roadhog
as Junkenstein's Monster
is pretty accurate.
A lot of people think the
monster is called Frankenstein,
but that's of course
the name of the doctor
from the book by Mary Shelley.
He's got a lot of amazing voice work
I've gone through in other videos,
so here's just a couple
of my favourite lines.
- [Roadhog] I'm alive!
They called me a monster,
so I'll be a monster.
- [Hammeh] Finally, although I don't think
it's quoted directly
by Roadhog or Junkrat,
although Ana's witness me
is an obvious reference,
Mad Max and the Australian
post-apocalyptic future
are clearly a big inspiration
for Roadhog and Junkrat.
The Many Mothers from Mad Max, Fury Road
were part of the visual
inspiration for Ana's look
and Junkrat and Roadhog's
whole design vibe
as well as their home and story
definitely is an homage to the films.
Roadhog doesn't have huge connexions
with the Overwatch cast.
A man of few words, of course,
he still has a few
interactions with Junkrat.
The troublesome twosome re
literally thick as thieves,
Roadhog's in it for the money as we know,
guarding Junkrat for a share
of the mysterious treasure
that he possesses.
Roadhog does grumble a
lot at Jamison Fawkes,
but however well they don't get on,
the two do seem to have
the occasional comedy moment together.
Roadhog of course complains
a lot about Junkrat.
- [Roadhog] Do you ever shut up?
Someday, I'm just gonna leave you.
- [Hammeh] And when Roadhog asks Junkrat
to stay out of trouble,
Junkrat swears that he will.
- [Roadhog] Try and stay
out of trouble for once.
- [Junkrat] I'll be on me best behaviour.
- [Hammeh] I don't think he's
been too successful on that.
Apparently Roadhog comes
up with the odd joke even,
according to Junkrat.
- [Junkrat] You won't believe the joke
old Pigface over there told
me the other day, right, Hog?
- [Roadhog] Do you ever shut up?
- [Hammeh] When Junkrat comments
on their combat techniques,
Roadhog doesn't want any of it.
- [Junkrat] You hook 'em, I'll cook 'em.
- [Roadhog] Shut up.
- [Hammeh] Roadhog will
occasionally come out
with this when he sees
an enemy Junkrat die.
- [Roadhog] Someone finally shut him up.
- [Hammeh] And when he
kills an enemy Junkrat,
he makes it quite clear
what his feelings are.
- [Roadhog] I'm tired
of hearing your voice.
- [Hammeh] When Roadhog
watches a Junkrat on his team
kill something, he's glad
to see Junkrat in action.
- [Roadhog] About time
you did something useful.
I'm always saving your skin.
- [Hammeh] Outside of Junkertown
and the Australian outback,
Roadhog's actually a
pretty well travelled guy.
An international crime spree
clearly gives excellent
travel opportunities.
He's been all over the
world, from Japan to Paris
and Mexico to the UK.
Although being his reserved self,
when it comes to speaking anyway,
Roadhog still only has a
little to say on a few maps.
We've seen and heard
about the Junker's crown
jewel caper in London
when they took a trip to King's Row.
It seems as though that
they didn't hang on
to the spoils of the robbery for long,
if Roadhog's King's Row spawn interaction
is anything to go by.
- [Roadhog] Pretty sure they're still mad
about those jewels we stole.
I miss that crown.
- [Hammeh] And when Junkrat
reminisces on the same caper,
Roadhog even has to remind
Junkrat of his name.
- [Junkrat] Ah, remember that time
we stole the crown jewels?
All hail King Jamison Fawkes the first!
And Duke Roadhog?
What is your name, anyways?
- [Roadhog] Mako.
- [Hammeh] On picturesque
maps such as Ilios and Nepal,
we see that Roadhog, or perhaps
Mako in a previous life,
still has a part of his soul
that appreciates beauty.
- [Roadhog] Pretty sure they're still mad
about those jewels we stole.
I miss that crown.
- [Hammeh] He'll probably
kill someone there anyway,
of course, but the thought
counts for something, right?
The Junkers robbed the bank
of Dorado at some point
as we can see from the
security camera footage
in the level and Roadhog's
signature canisters
strewn across the vault,
as well as the map present on the level.
Roadhog has some fond memories of Dorado,
its vaults, and of course the gold within.
- [Roadhog] Ooh, they stocked up again.
Now I know why they call
this place Dorado. (laughing)
- [Hammeh] Dorado's very name, of course,
is most likely a nod to El Dorado,
a 16th or so century
myth of a city or empire
of golden wealth in South America.
Roadhog knowing a little
of his South American
and Spanish conquistador history there.
Thanks very much for tuning in
to my hero voiceline and story series.
Do check the playlist
linked here on the left
for more videos like
this of different heroes.
If you liked this video,
please hit that like button below,
subscribe, and comment with
what lines you enjoy most
as well as what Overwatch lore topics
you'd like to see covered.
I really appreciate
hearing what you all think.
Big thanks to all of my patrons on Patreon
who make these longer videos possible.
Please do check out the link here too.
Until next time, I've been Hammeh.
Take it easy.